<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letters and papers concerning some matters in the last Parliament relating to the commou [sic] rights of all the Commnns [sic] of England, fit to be considered in the next, and by all the said Commons in the mean time.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1704</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61431</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5428C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC T63879</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834476</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834476</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38977</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61431)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38977)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2063:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Letters and papers concerning some matters in the last Parliament relating to the commou [sic] rights of all the Commnns [sic] of England, fit to be considered in the next, and by all the said Commons in the mean time.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2],2;4;4;4;[4]+p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700 [1704]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The letters are signed: Edward Stephens.</note>
                  <note>The last numbered part bears the colophon: printed in the year 1701. The [4] p. at end are dated: June 19. 1704. There is a MS. date of: 17 Apr. 1705.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; text incomplete, catchwords on p. [4] of unpaginated sequence: A second.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38977:1"/>
            <p>LETTERS and PAPERS Concerning ſome MATTERS in the laſt PARLIAMENT, Relating to the <hi>Common Rights</hi> of all the <hi>Communs of England,</hi> Fit to be Conſidered in the next, And by all the ſaid COMMONS In the mean time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the Author in the Year 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="paper">
                  <pb facs="tcp:38977:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38977:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the Knights, Gentlemen and Free-Holders of the County of</hi> Glouceſter.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THough I have left the Employments of the World, I have not left off my Love and Good Will to my Country; either the Nation in general, or your particular County: And therefore ſince you are e're long to have a New Election of Members of Parliament, I think ſit to give you Notice of ſome things fit to be conſidered in Relation to that Buſineſs; a Buſineſs, which deſerves to be better conſidered by all the Commons of <hi>England</hi> than it has been hitherto. But what does concern the Nation in General is fit to be ſaid to all, and ſomething of that has been ſaid already. 'Tis what does more eſpecially concern your County that I ſhall here offer to your Conſideration. The Denial of Juſtice has been always look upon as a great Grievance in a King, but a Capital Crime in a Subject. The Preſervation of our Rights, and of the free Courſe of Juſtice is a principal part of the Truſt repoſed in our Repreſentatives in Parliament. To prefer our Petitions for matters of Common Concern to the Houſe of Commons is as much the Right of every Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner of <hi>England,</hi> as to prefer an Indictment to a Grand Jury in a County. And as the Miſdemeanors of a particular Grand Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-man may be preſented and enquired of by another Grand Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the Miſdemeanors of a whole Jury upon an Attaint; So, the Miſdemeanors not only of particular Members, but of a whole Houſe, or a whole Parliament, may be Corrected and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed in another; and the Crimes of particular leading Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers Puniſhed.</p>
                  <p>This great, fundamental, and important Right, has been twice within few years, violated, denied, or hindered and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, by Members of your County; Firſt by one ſince de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, who, having a Petition to preſent againſt the Speaker and another Member, for no leſs a Crime than diſcouraging the Execution of the Law and Contempt of her late Majeſties Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; for Proof of which, there were no leſs than ſeven Biſhops, beſides other conſiderable Perſons, Witneſſes, did by Contrivance
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38977:3"/>with the Criminals ſo time it, that at laſt, after much delay, it was by a ſmall Number of the Members gotten together with the Speaker, thrown out without Reading. This was ſoon after complained of at the General Quarter Seſſions, and the Petition left with the Clerk of the Peace: And now again in the laſt Seſſion of Parliament in ſuch manner, as is a Shame to themſelves, the whole <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> and indeed to the whole Nation to have had ſuch a Set of Repreſentatives: and moſt Juſt it was upon them, that they, who had no more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Honour of the King, nay, to the Honour of God himſelf, ſhould be ſo infatuated as to expoſe their own Shame, and the Shame of the whole Houſe, and to the farther Shame of the Nation, if it be ſuffered to Paſs without due Correction. The Caſe is ſo plain and eaſie to be underſtood by the other two Papers hereunto annexed, that I need ſay no more, than, as to Mr. <hi>How</hi> (whoſe Name I ſpared, but they Printed) that the Words alledged to have been ſpoken by him to my ſelf, I can ſafely Teſtifie upon Oath, if there were occaſion, but I preſume he will not deny them. And as for Sir <hi>Richard Cox,</hi> I had by a former Letter imminded him of the former Caſe; but it ſeems he was not ſo much concerned for your Rights, as ever to move any thing concerning that. But upon the motion of this, by a Perſon, if I be not miſinformed, who had given ſuch Proofs of his Diſ-reſpect, at ſeveral times, both to King and Commons, that I have before now wondered that he hath been ſo long permitted to have any Place in an Engliſh Parliament; he was not only pleaſed to make a Wiſe Speech, as he thought in the Houſe, but to repeat it out of the Houſe in <hi>Coffee-houſes,</hi> and <hi>Taverns,</hi> with ſo much Vanity, and ſo palpable Falſity, that the very peruſal of theſe Papers are ſufficient to detect it, and as gave Offence to divers who heard him, and made ſome think a little Addition to his Name at the end, more proper for him than that before it.</p>
                  <p>I preſume you know who are concerned in the Caſe, and hope you will do at your County Court, what may be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Indication, of your Senſe of Religion, of your Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Regard to the Noble Conſtitution of our Government, and your Concern for the Common Rights of the Commons of <hi>England.</hi> And indeed, it is a kind of unavoidable Teſt of all theſe.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Humble Servant</hi> Edw. Stephens.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="questions">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38977:3"/>
                  <head>QUESTIONS OF Common Right, <hi>Proper and Neceſſary</hi> to be conſidered by all <hi>Knights, Gentlemen, Free-hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and</hi> Commoners of England, <hi>and eſpecially thoſe of the Honourable Profeſſion of the Law.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE true</hi> Engliſh <hi>Government,</hi> excellently compoſed of the three Simple Species, <hi>Monarchy, Ariſtocracy,</hi> and <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy,</hi> I have long thought, and ſtill think, to be <hi>in its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,</hi> one of the <hi>Beſt</hi> Governments in the World; and not more excellent in it ſelf, than well <hi>Accommodated</hi> to the Genius of the People; and which is but the conſequence of theſe, moſt <hi>Eaſy to be Exerciſed.</hi> This I think very true, tho' it hath already within our Memory, ſuffer'd ſuch diſmal <hi>Concuſſions and Confuſions,</hi> and, in my apprehenſion, is in in ſo great Danger of more, as if there was nothing of Truth in it. But this doth not proceed from the Conſtitution; but from other <hi>Cauſes:</hi> Whereof one is <hi>Secret, The Judgment of God,</hi> for a ſecret <hi>Root of Bitterneſs,</hi> little regarded by thoſe, who ought to be moſt Skilful in diſcerning, and moſt Active in amending ſuch Matters. But there are others manifeſt enough: One is a General <hi>Corruption of the Manners</hi> of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38977:4"/>the People: Another notorious <hi>Corruption of their Deputies and Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives,</hi> both in <hi>Manners</hi> in general, and in reſpect of <hi>Juſtice and the Truſt</hi> repoſed in them; in which reſpect, I have known ſome of themſelves laugh, and ſay, that they are <hi>the true Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives of the Nation</hi> indeed. And tho' this of it ſelf hath a Tendence to the Diſſolution of the Government, yet there is another more dangerous than this, if it be not look'd to in time: and that is by <hi>Popular Factions.</hi> For as Monarchies are apt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate into Tyranny, ſo Democracies are as apt to be diſſolv'd by Factions: And tho' in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſtitution there is as good Proviſion againſt both theſe, as <hi>Humane</hi> Affairs are capable of, yet are the Parts of which it is conſtituted, ſubject in ſome ſort, to the Corruptions of thoſe ſimple Species, from which they are derived. What was it but a ſecret Faction in the Long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which firſt caſt out the Biſhops as Popiſhly affected, then the Lords as Uſeleſs and Dangerous, then the greateſt part of the Commons, except themſelves, commonly call'd, <hi>The Rump;</hi> then cut off the King's Head; and brought all into ſuch Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as could never be ſettled, until the old Form was reſtored again? What was it but a Faction, which by no leſs than three ſeveral Acts of Parliament engag'd the Clergy, the Corporations, the Militia, and all the great Officers and Magiſtrates of the Nation, in ſuch Declarations, as juſtify or excuſe the Adverſaries of the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution and make the Severities againſt them and Pretence of Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, inexcuſable, unjuſt, and unreaſonable? What is it but a Faction, which hath preſum'd with ſo much Inſolence to offer ſuch Indignities to a Prince of ſo Great Courage and Conduct, as hath been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly believed and talk'd to have been on purpoſe to affront him? How near have ſuch Factions gone to inſlave the Nation, and ſet up the Monarchy to be Abſolute and Arbitrary? And how fairly have they begun to pull down that, and the Ariſtrocratical part, and ſet up the Democracy, or themſelves and they know not what; or rather to introduce an Anarchy, and turn all into the like Confuſions again. What ſuch things may come to in time, if neglected, no man knows; but what may be done to prevent the Miſchief, is fit to be conſidered. Miſcarriages of Juries may be enquir'd into: And what is done amiſs in one Parliament may be rectified in another. And where there is manifeſtly a Truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and ſo great a Truſt, it would be ſuch a Fault in this Conſtitution as I never ſuſpected, if it might be falſiſied in ſuch Matters as theſe, and without Remedy. I have therefore thought
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38977:4"/>fit to propoſe the following QUESTIONS to the Conſideration of all Perſons concern'd, who think fit to concern themſelves with them. But into ſo great Degeneracy, Corruption of Manners and Audacious Impiety, is this Nation Sunk, That it is rare to meet with Men, who dare to do their Duty, or ſo much as aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert their Common Rights, or the very Religion they Profeſs, notwithſtanding the Laws both of God and Man on their ſide, and even where they have not only the greateſt <hi>Obligation,</hi> but the greateſt <hi>Priviledge</hi> to do it that can be. This is manifeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all Contradiction by ſome late Actions of great Infolence, and no leſs Impiety: So that unleſs <hi>another Parliament,</hi> and a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of the Clergy</hi> take the Matter into good Conſideration, and provide a ſpeedy Remedy, there is great Danger that the whole Nation will ſpeedily fall into great Confuſion.</p>
                  <p>The QUESTIONS are theſe:</p>
                  <p n="1">I. Whether the ſeveral <hi>Members of the Houſe of Commons</hi> be not <hi>Authoriſed</hi> to Sit and Act there, by their reſpective Counties, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Burroughs, by Indenture under the Hands and Seals of the Principal Electors for themſelves and the reſt, as Deputies and Truſtees for them all?</p>
                  <p n="2">II. Whether they ought not to <hi>receive Inſtructions</hi> from, and in all Matters of moment <hi>conſult</hi> and adviſe with their Principals?</p>
                  <p n="3">III. Whether it be not <hi>the Right and Duty of every</hi> Knight, Gentleman, Freehold, and <hi>Commoner</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> to repreſent to the Houſe of Commons by their proper Repreſentatives, or any other Member of the Houſe, all ſuch matters of Publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern as are proper to be enquir'd of and conſidered there?</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. Whether any <hi>Commoner</hi> of <hi>England</hi> may not require his proper Repreſentative to repreſent any ſuch Matter to the Houſe?</p>
                  <p n="5">V. Whether it be not a Breach of Truſt in any ſuch Deputy or Repreſentative not to perform what is ſo required honeſtly and faithfully?</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. Whether they be not <hi>accountable for their Behaviour</hi> in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to their Principals, by and for whom they are deputed and intruſted; that is, <hi>queſtionable</hi> by thoſe of the Counties in their County Court (to which all owe Suit and Service, but many neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect it to their common Prejudice) and thoſe of the Cities and Burroughs in their reſpective proper Courts and Aſſemblies, and <hi>Puniſhable</hi> for any notorious Breach of their Truſt upon Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint in Parliament?</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:38977:5"/>
                  <p n="7">VII. Whether <hi>Matters</hi> touching the Honour of Religion, the Honour of the King, the common Right of all the Commoners of <hi>England,</hi> and the Encouragement, or Diſcouragement of the Execution of the Laws, be not <hi>proper</hi> Matters to be repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, enquired and conſidered there?</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII Whether it be not <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nparliamentary,</hi> a Breach of Truſt, and great <hi>Violation of a Fundamental Right of all the Commoners of England,</hi> for a ſmall number of the Members with their Speaker before the Houſe be full, <hi>to Vote that a Petition Exhibited for any ſuch Matter,</hi> as aforeſaid, <hi>ſhould not be read?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">IX. Whether it be Parliamentary or agreeable to the uſual Courſe of Parliaments, <hi>to Vote a Petition or Letter of Complaint</hi> for any Contempt of Religion, or Diſhonour or Indignity to the King, or Factions, or Seditious Practices, to be a falſe and ſcandalous Libel, and the Complainant to be proſecuted before he hath been heard at the Bar, or had notice to appear and prove his Complaint?</p>
                  <p n="10">X. Whether the Fundamental and <hi>Common Rights of all the Commons of England</hi> be not of greater Importance to be Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and Maintained Inviolably than any of the <hi>Priviledges of their Deputies,</hi> which they have only in Reſpect of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation and Truſt repoſed in them (of which ſome are often Complained of by their Principals as Abuſed to their Prejudice?)</p>
                  <p n="11">XI. Whether it be not the <hi>Common Intereſt</hi> of the Government of <hi>England,</hi> and of all the Commons, and the <hi>Duty of every Subject</hi> to maintain and defend the Honour and Dignity of the King, when there is occaſion, as well as the Rights and Liberties of themſelves, and their Fellow-Commoners, by the Common Law of Loyalty and Allegiance, and of all Members of Parliament, Magiſtrates and Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by ſpecial Obligation of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Oath?</p>
                  <p n="12">XII. Whether all Conſpiracies and Practices which have a natural Tendency to diſſolve, interrupt, or abate the mutual Conſidence that ought to be preſerved and maintain'd between the King and the People, and to draw the Affections of the People from the King to the Conſpirators; eſpecially when on the one ſide there is no ſpecial Occaſion for them more than ordinary; and on the other, there are ſuch Popular Matters in agitation as give great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to ſuch a Deſign, may not juſtly be ſuſpected to be Treaſonable, and by Conſequence ought to be ſtoutly and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely oppoſed by all <hi>Faithful</hi> and <hi>Loyal</hi> Subjects?</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:38977:5"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the Knights, Gentlemen, Freeholders and Commons of</hi> England, <hi>EDWARD STEPHENS wiſheth Prudence, Piety, Peace and Happineſs.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentlemen and Fellow-Commoners,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>VVHat you ſee here <hi>Open</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> to divers Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, your Truſtees and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>ſentatives in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being then printed, not to be publiſh'd, but only a ſmall number to be preſented to them. But ſince they have pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bubliſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d their
<note n="*" place="margin">V. Old Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Loyalty. <hi>p.</hi> 13.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Votes</hi> concerning it; 'tis fit and but juſt you ſhould ſee what it is they have ſo Cenſur'd. I have many years endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to ſerve you to the beſt of my Ability, without ſeeking Preferment or Reward from Men, or accepting of what hath been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd. What I have written lately for the Service of our Great Maſter and your Selves, hath been ill requited by the Prudential
<note n="*" place="margin">A name not impoſed, but aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly.</note> 
                     <hi>Latitudina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Biſhops with Falſe Reports and Calumnies, no leſs than of <hi>Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Popery,</hi> like the <hi>Falſe Prophets</hi> of old, and the <hi>Incendiaries</hi> of the late Civil Wars: And what I have offer'd to the Houſe for the ſame purpoſe, both formerly, and now again, hath been ſo treated as is very inconſiſtent either with their Duty or our Right. For theſe things <hi>I appeal</hi> to the Righteous Judgment of Almighty God, to your own Conſciences, and to the next Parliament; and to a Convention of the Clergy, as to what concerns the Biſhops and the falſe Charge of Popery. Theſe Gentlemen, who ſet up themſelves for <hi>our Maſters,</hi> receive all their Authority from Us, and under our Hands and Seals; and if we do not let them know they are our <hi>our Servants,</hi> and accountable to Us for their Behaviour, We our ſelves are juſtly anſwerable for their Misbehaviour before God and Man. And if we do not appear as well for the Honour of the King, when there is occaſion, as for the Rights of the Subject, we do not diſcharge our Duty to our Country, perform our Oath to the King, or are Worthy of the Benefit of ſo Noble a Government. I hope you will look better to your Election the next time, and ſend up ſuch Perſons as have more ſenſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38977:6"/>and their Duty to God, of the true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, and the Honour of the Ring, of your Rights and the Truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in them, and fit to enquire into the Miſcarriages of theſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>To Sir <hi>Richard Cocks.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir <hi>Richard,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>AS I am a Commoner of <hi>England,</hi> it is, as I told you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, my Right and my Duty to take notice, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> of all, or any ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of publick Concern as are proper for the Inquiry or Conſideration of that Houſe. And as I am a Chriſtian, I am much more obliged to uſe that Right, and diſcharge that Duty, when they are ſuch as do affront, or do Contempt to the Chriſtian Religion, which is the Religion of the Nation, and ſo Eſſential a part of this Conſtitution, that it is one of the Fundamental Principles of our Laws, that what-ever Laws are enacted in any thing contrary to this Religion, they are ſo far void and null. This is the common Right and Duty of every Commoner of <hi>England.</hi> But beſides all this, I have been for ſome Years, by the ſpecial Providence of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, engaged in his more immediate Service, and without limitation to any ſpecial Charge; ſo that where-ever I have oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity for his Service, I am obliged ſaithfully to diſcharge it. And beſides all this, I am obliged by Oath to be faithful to the preſent King, which I intend, by the Grace of God, faithfully to perform, tho' for ſpecial, and, I think, good Reaſons, I refuſe to take it again. Theſe are great Obligations, and ſuch as I cannot diſcharge without taking notice and complaining of what I obſerve greatly amiſs in <hi>Both Houſes of Parliament.</hi> And I ſhall do it firſt to you, as my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Repreſentative; and by you deſire it may be repreſented to the Houſe, as you will anſwer it to your Country, for which you ſerve.</p>
                  <p>In your Houſe I obſerve ſuch abominable Impiety, and Contempt of Religion, as greater hath rarely been known: I have heard it complained of by Members of the Houſe, that a Man can hardly mention any thing of God or Religion there, but he ſhall be in danger to be ridicul'd or laught at. And when I have asked, why no body moved the Houſe that ſome of them might be called to the Bar, and made Examples, the common Anſwer hath been, <hi>It would be to no purpoſe.</hi> Which is the Shame of the whole Houſe, and notorious Evidence of their Impudence and Ignorance of what becomes ſuch Aſſemblies, in one part of them; and of ſuch Baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38977:6"/>as makes them unworthy of the Name of Chriſtians in the reſt; as if the generous Diſcharge of ſo great and noble a Duty, was not of it ſelf a thing to great purpoſe; as if the Fearful, or ſuch as are aſhamed of Chriſt, or his Words, are not to have their part with Infidels and Unbelievers; <hi>that is,</hi> with ſuch as the reſt of their Fellow-Members of whom they complain; as if their Baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs might not reaſonably be imputed by the others to Infidelity and Disbelief of the Religion, which they profeſs, to the Scandal of Religion, and Hardening thoſe poor Creatures in their Impiety. It is no wonder if the whole-Nation abound in Infidelity, and all kind of Wickedneſs, when there is no more Religion in thoſe who ſhould correct it among the Commons, and the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Of their Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentials, I have long ſince no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on the Action at Sea, <hi>p.</hi> 29, 30, 31 <hi>and another lately in my</hi> Narrative, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides others elſewhere.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops among the Lords. And now I appeal to the Conſciences of all, who have any Senſe of Religion, and to the dreadful Tribunal of Almighty God, whether theſe things be not true, and whether there be not more danger to the Nation from ſuch a <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Biſhops,</hi> than from <hi>Popery,</hi> and from all the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites</hi> in the Nation, if they were as many more as they are.</p>
                  <p>And where there is no more Fear of God, it is no wonder if there be not that Honour and Reſpect for the King, that there ought to be: Freedom of Debates in Parliament is undoubtedly the Right of the Subject: But if under pretence of Freedom of Debates any Members ſhall do acts of Inſolence and Diſreſpect to the King, that is no part of their Right, but a Violation of Duty to the King, and tending to the Diſſolution of the Government, and ought to be corrected.</p>
                  <p>That your late <hi>Votes,</hi> grounded upon a falſe and fooliſh Letter to a Member of Parliament, was ſuch, is believed by many, to get an advantage againſt the King; and to prevent that, 'tis likely many did comply in their Votes, who did not ſee any other reaſon for it; and the Choice of the Chairman for that Committee, a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who was turn'd out of her Service by the late good Queen, hath declared openly in your Lobby to my ſelf, that he thought Vice ought to be encouraged, and is reported to have expreſſed no little diſreſpect to the King in your Houſe before now, is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Aggravation of the Indignity. How ſuch things can be conſiſtent either with Conſcience and Religion, Civil Duty to our Country, and one of the beſt Governments in the World, or their Oaths of Fidelity to the King, I do not underſtand: Nor ſo much as with common Prudence for themſelves, and their own Rights. The King hath ſhewed himſelf a Prince of great Courage, and of as great Prudence and Conduct. Almighty God has by him, as his Inſtrument, in Confederacy with divers of the chief Catholick Princes, vouchſafed us a happy Peace, if we have the Diſcretion to uſe it as we ought, and as becomes Perſons ſenſible of his Goodneſs,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38977:7"/>and of the Reſpect they ought to have for his Inſtruments in it. But I doubt theſe Politicians do but egregiouſly befool themſelves with a vain Conceit add Preſumption of having the Purſe of the Nation. For certainly the King hath as little need of them, as they have of him: And by ſuch Politicks they do but provoke the juſt Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not only of a wiſe Prince, but of all honeſt and faithful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and moſt of all, of thoſe Confederates, who, if this King ſhould die, as he muſt one day, may by the juſt Judgment of God, enter into a Confederacy of themſelves to correct their Ingratitude and Folly. Nay, ſhould the King but diſſolve this Parliament, and in a Declaration ſet out ſuch Reaſons as he may for that, and for Calling of another, their little Politicks with themſelves might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably be ſoon in the dirt. The <hi>Pretence of the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>There are other more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, natural, and effectual Means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move all Fear of</hi> Popery, <hi>than ſuch Violence of Factions: of which the King cannot but know ſomething.</hi>
                        </note> Growth of Popery</hi> hath been made uſe of to ſo ill purpoſe heretofore; hath ſo little ground at this time, more than what proceeds from the Negligence of the Clergy in aſſiſting condemned Perſons, and viſiting the Sick, and the Obſtinacy and Unconcernedneſs of a Party-of Prudential <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinarian</hi> Biſhops, for what does more properly belong to their Charge, and particularly for mending their Cauſe, and making that ſound, which is indefenſible at preſent: and is raiſed, I believe, ſo unſeaſonably to ſerve and ſupport a lame and tottering Cauſe, that 'tis like to prove the Shame and Confuſion both of it, and of thoſe who make uſe of ſuch indirect Means for that purpoſe. Let me but know who were the Compoſers of that Letter, and had the Impudence and Folly to call me (as it is commonly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood) <hi>Madman Convert,</hi> (two Lyes at once) and I do not doubt but to give you ſuch Account of the whole Matter, as will ſufficiently ſatifie both the Houſe and all honeſt and wiſe Men in the Nation. What I have more to ſay, I ſhall reſerve till I ſee what Uſe is made of this. I hope the Houſe will conſider what is to be done, both to <hi>expiate</hi> that provoking Wickedneſs againſt God, and to <hi>Correct,</hi> as they deſerve, all Indignities done to the King: and you ſhall always find me ready, in what belongs to me, to ſerve Both, and my Country, in the beſt manner I can.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your humble Servant,</hi> Edward Stephens.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="paper">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38977:7"/>
                  <head>THE CORRUPTION AND IMPIETY OF THE <hi>Common Members</hi> OF THE Late Houſe of COMMONS.</head>
                  <p>IT is with the Beſt <hi>Governments,</hi> that all the Wit and Foreſight of Man can deviſe, as it is with Material <hi>Buildings.</hi> They are both alike ſubject to <hi>Decays,</hi> which if not repaired in due time, inevitably bring Ruin and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction at laſt. The <hi>true Engliſh Government</hi> is both in it ſelf one of the beſt Conſtitutions in the World, and moſt accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date to the Nature and Genius of the <hi>Engliſh People.</hi> And <hi>the People of this Nation</hi> have been heretofore as Famous, not only for Courage and Hardineſs, but alſo for Wiſdom, Virtue and Piety, as any People in the World. But at this preſent, both the Government is fallen into great Decay, and the People become ſo degenerate, that they are like to become the Scorn and <hi>Odium</hi> of all the reſt of Mankind, if Matters be not ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amended. The whole Nation has ſeemed to me for ſome time, as under an <hi>Enchantment.</hi> And I have known thoſe, who in reſpect to the Notorious <hi>Corruption of the Houſe of Commons,</hi> have jeſtingly ſaid, They were True Repreſentatives of the People; and yet when they themſelves have gotten In amongſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38977:8"/>them, have done nothing worthy of the Name of <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> toward any Amendment, much leſs of Chriſtians, though Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Religion of no ordinary Form.</p>
                  <p>The Writers of <hi>Magick</hi> tell us, That ſuch as are Initiate and Proficients in the <hi>Black Art,</hi> can by the Aſſiſtance of their <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Spirits,</hi> ſo bind People in ſome Particulars, that in thoſe Particulars they cannot accompliſh any thing, though in all others they act as other People; and divers ſuch have I ſeen and diſcourſed with. And whole Families have I known brought to Deſolation, in ſuch manner as ſeemed very plain to me, to be by the ſecret Operations of ſome inviſible intelligent Powers, or ſome <hi>Secret Curſe,</hi> which did adhere to them, or both. And in ſome I have known a certain and manifeſt Cauſe, and I doubt not, but there was the like in others, but unknown to any but ſuch as would not diſcover it. And this I have great reaſon to believe is the true Caſe of this Nation; which will appear in time. But it is too ſober a Subject for ſo mad a Generation to be farther diſcourſed at preſent.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Corruptions of the Houſe of Commons</hi> is, what is at preſent neceſſary to be conſider'd, and is ſo Notorious, as needs not many Words to prove it. It hath been a <hi>common and known Practice</hi> for this Forty Years laſt paſt; for Men of Confidence and ready Elocution, if they could but procure an Election in ſome little Mercenary Burrough, and ſo get into the Houſe, preſently to ſet themſelves to oppoſe the King and the Court, that they might be bought off by ſome good <hi>Gratuity, Penſion,</hi> or <hi>Place:</hi> and one while to Treat the King with the greateſt Inſolence and Indignity; and another time the whole Houſe of Commons; and this either lightly laugh'd at, or gravely and prudentially paſſed by, by the reſt. Have we not ſeen after ſufficient Inſolence to the King on one ſide, afterwards the whole Houſe of Commons Adjourned by the ſame Perſon, their Speaker, without; nay, againſt their Conſent, to pleaſe him; and yet this Gentleman permitted conſtantly to be a Member to this Day? And what a Noiſe and Clamour had we lately of the <hi>Growth of Popery,</hi> and a moſt unreaſonable Act paſſed upon it, when the Myſtery of all was no other than to Lower King <hi>William</hi>'s Reputation with his Confederates beyond Sea, and ingratiate themſelves with the Abuſed People at home? Whether theſe things do not tend to the Diſſolution of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38977:8"/>Government, and to introduce a Commonwealth, like to end in Anarchy and Confuſion, as heretofore, is not hard to be reſolved, and deſerves to be well conſider'd in time. And it may be worth the Conſideration, Whether the Myſtery of ſome Peoples <hi>Heat about the Succeſſion</hi> be not in the bottom to make that a Step to the Alteration of the Government? So that there ſeems <hi>two Dangerous Corruptions</hi> in the late Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Houſe of Commons; the one <hi>the Trade of Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Members,</hi> of which I have mentioned but little of what is known, or upon good grounds believed or ſuſpected; whereby the common Intereſt of the People is bought and ſold by theſe Traders, or Traitors if you will; the other <hi>a Conſpiracy of a most wicked Faction</hi> of Apoſtates, Deiſts, Socinians and Latudinarians, to ſubvert the Government, under pretence of Preſerving the Rights of the People; and to caſt out Chriſtianity, under pretence of Securing the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And how little there is of true Religion amongſt any of them all is Notorious by their Actions in <hi>the two laſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments,</hi> upon the <hi>Letters</hi> in Print to Sir <hi>Richard Cocks,</hi> and to the Knights, Gentlemen and Freeholders, and <hi>Commons of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> What a <hi>Charge of Impiety</hi> is there upon the whole Houſe of Commons! And what a ſilly and impious Vote was paſs'd upon it! And how Hypocritically and Scandalouſly have this laſt deſervedly ſhort-liv'd Houſe of Commons behaved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their Formal <hi>Addreſs</hi> for a Solemn Day of <hi>Fasting and Prayer</hi> for the Bleſſing of God upon their Conſultations; and yet not one of them all ſo much as open his Mouth for a due Correction of ſo great Impiety.</p>
                  <p>It is certain and unqueſtionable, that being <hi>aſhamed of Chriſt or his Words,</hi> and <hi>giving Offence or Scandal to Religion,</hi> are <hi>Two Capital Crimes</hi> in the Laws of the Goſpel, and terrible and ſevere Judgments denounced againſt them. And nothing can be more <hi>Scandalous</hi> to Religion, than for a Man to make a high Profeſſion of Religion, and be aſhamed or afraid to ſpeak for it, when there is ſo juſt and neceſſary occaſion. So that the Sin and Danger of ſuch Perſons in the Houſe, I take to be the greateſt of all, and that which is like to ſeal up ſome Judgment of God upon the whole Nation, if ſome proper Courſe be not ſpeedily taken to prevent it.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:38977:9"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God</hi> hath already anſwered them in their own kind: for he hath the Hearts of <hi>Kings</hi> in his hands, and turns them as the Rivers of Water: And if the <hi>People</hi> have not now a Care that they chooſe none of them again, they who do otherwiſe may poſſibly find the <hi>Curſe</hi> cleave to themſelves, and to thoſe they chooſe. And as the <hi>King</hi> has done well to Diſſolve them, ſo if he pleaſe to conſult his Judges, and the Learned in the Law, it is like he will find matter enough to Correct the Inſolence of ſome of the moſt active <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators.</hi> And then it may be hoped, we may ſee a true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament again. And then it may alſo be hoped we may ſee the Decays, which have been too long neglected, effectually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired.</p>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Part of the Letter to Sir</hi> RICHARD COCKS.</head>
                     <p>In your Houſe I obſerve ſuch abominable Impiety, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Religion, as greater hath rarely been known: I have heard it complained of by Members of the Houſe, that a Man can hardly mention any thing of God or Religion there, but he ſhall be in danger to be ridicul'd or laught at. And when I have asked, Why no body moved the Houſe, that ſome of them might de called to the Bar, and made Examples? The common Anſwer hath been, <hi>It would be to no purpoſe.</hi> Which is the Shame of the whole Houſe, and notorious Evidence of their Impudence and Ignorance of what becomes ſuch Aſſemblies, in one part of them; and of ſuch Baſeneſs, as makes them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the Name of Chriſtians in the reſt; as if the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Diſcharge of ſo great and noble a Duty, was not of it ſelf a thing to great purpoſe; as if the Fearful, or ſuch as are aſhamed of Chriſt, or his Words, are not to have their part with Infidels and Unbelievers; <hi>that is,</hi> with ſuch as the reſt of their Fellow-Members of whom they complain; as if their Baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs might not reaſonably be imputed by the others to Infidelity and Disbelief of the Religion, which they profeſs, to the Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of Religion, and Hardening thoſe poor Creatures in their Impiety. It is no wonder if the whole Nation abound in Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, and all kind of Wickedneſs, when there is no more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in thoſe who ſhould correct it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Letters at Large with other Papers, may be had at the</hi> New-Inn <hi>Coffee-Houſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed in the Year 1701.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="paper">
                  <pb facs="tcp:38977:9"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the Knights, Gentlemen, Freeholders and Commons of</hi> England.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentlemen and Fellow-Commoners,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THO I have given ſufficient <hi>Demonſtration</hi> to all thoſe few who know me, of my <hi>good Will, Readineſs, and Reſolution for your Service,</hi> yet ſuch has been the Malice of ſome wicked men to <hi>defame</hi> me, which I could have born patiently did it not diſable me to ſerve you, as I would, that I'm compel'd, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> was, to ſay thoſe things for my ſelf, but for your ſake, which nothing leſs ſhould have extorted from me.</p>
                  <p>I have liv'd now in the World above the ordinary <hi>Age</hi> of Man. My <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Study</hi> from my Youth has been the Service of God and of my Country, upon all <hi>Occaſions,</hi> which I always look'd upon as Calls to me. I always hated <hi>Knavery</hi> and <hi>Falſhood,</hi> and was zealous for <hi>Truth and Righteouſneſs;</hi> tho I have ſometimes been miſtaken in <hi>matters of fact</hi> of others, yet never in my <hi>Principles</hi> that I remember, or varied from them in deliberate Actions, ſo as to be juſtly charg'd by Man, tho I dare not juſtify my ſelf before the ſtrict Juſtice of God. I have ſpent my Life in this Service without ſoliciting for <hi>Preferment,</hi> or ſo much as accepting what has been offer'd me both in Church and State. And to ſay nothing of former times, I prov'd my ſelf <hi>a Faithful Monitor</hi> to the late King and Queen, and to my Country, all his time from firſt to laſt, and ſo as I doubt not but Poſterity will approve, whatever the preſent Generation doth: and ſhould have done the like in the preſent Reign, had I had the like Opportunities, nor have I been wanting in what I could do.</p>
                  <p>I drew a Specimen of a <hi>Declaration againſt Debauchery,</hi> before the Prince came to <hi>London,</hi> which being approv'd by conſiderable Perſons, was ſoon after deliver'd to him, and the Care of it recommended to one, whoſe Advantages were no leſs than his Duty to have promoted it: After he came to the Crown, I preſented him with a moſt faithful Admonition of what moſt concern'd him, and not only then complain'd in print of the ſhameful neglect of the <hi>Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Religion</hi> in Foreign Parts, and of <hi>Reformation of Manners</hi> at home, but ſome time after actually begun that neceſſary Work, and had undoubtedly brought it to a good Effect ſpeedily, had not ſuch as were actually engag'd in it, and ſuch as were moſt of all oblig'd to promote it, unworthily deſerted it, and ſet up <hi>a little ſuperficial Formality</hi> inſtead of it, which hath more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd it to Contempt by great Ones, than promoted it among Inferiours.</p>
                  <p>I gave you not only Notice, but Example too, how to correct <hi>the Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of your Truſtees in Parliament,</hi> and to make them know, that they are not your <hi>Maſters</hi> but your <hi>Servants;</hi> but ſuch as are moſt like to undo you, if you look not better to them, and conſider their Behaviour at your County Courts and General Quarter Seſſions.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38977:10"/>
                  <p>Conſidering of how great importance it is to have a <hi>Good Cauſe</hi> in all Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and how much Religion is really concerned or pretended in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent War, I began before it broke out again, in a Diſcourſe dedicated to the Judges, to ſhew the neceſſity of mending our Cauſe in matters of Religion. And have ſo aſſerted the Truth in ſeveral Particulars againſt four ſeveral Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that not any one of any of them all has yet appear'd publickly to reſiſt it (otherwiſe than by Lies and Calumnies, and diſcouraging the Bookſellers from printing or ſelling my Writings) or defend their own Cauſe againſt me; a thing perhaps never known before, ſince Printing was known; and an Atteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to Truth not inferiour to a Miracle, being a plain accompliſhment of our Saviour's Promiſe.</p>
                  <p>Moſt of theſe things have been preſented to the Lower Houſe of <hi>Convocation,</hi> where they reſt in Peace. And I have done the like in Civil Matters by juſt Repreſentations to our <hi>Repreſentatives in Parliament:</hi> But there not only Truth and Juſtice has been diſregarded, but one of our principal fundamental Rights violated, by thoſe, whoſe principal Truſt and Buſineſs it is to take Care to preſerve 'em. And ſeveral Papers of this ſort, with others of a Collection, intituled, <hi>A Meſſage of Peace,</hi> &amp;c. being ſtifled by the former Artifice, this Nation ſeems now in the miſerable Condition of the <hi>Jews</hi> of old lamented by the Prophet, <hi>Jſa.</hi> 59.14, 15.</p>
                  <p>I could tell you of divers <hi>other Maters,</hi> both Civil, and relating to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as for the better ordering of the <hi>Revenues of the Church</hi> in populous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, for more Aſſiſtants to take care of the Souls of the People; for better Proviſion for the neceſſary <hi>Preparation of condemned Perſons</hi> for their Execution; for better and more reaſonable <hi>Correction for Criminals</hi> than our common Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions; and for ſuch <hi>Reformation of our Gaols and Priſons,</hi> which are now the Nurſeries of all Vice and Wickedneſs, that they may be made Schools of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: All things very <hi>neceſſary,</hi> which I have endeavour'd to promote, but with ſuch Succeſs, as, with the like in others, tempt me to ſuſpect <hi>the whole Nation to be</hi> in ſome ſort <hi>under that wicked Power,</hi> whoſe <hi>Effigies</hi> is plac'd in the Place of the Croſs, upon the chief Spire of the City; eſpecially when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> has been <hi>acted,</hi> how the <hi>Nation</hi> has been <hi>abus'd,</hi> and the Judgments <hi>of God provok'd</hi> by ſuch Myſteries of Iniquity, as affront his <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcience,</hi> as well as his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> harden ſuch as are concern'd in them in Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zacy, now call'd Deiſm, and little leſs than Atheiſin, and would ſill the Minds of all ſober People with Horror, were they but commonly known and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. But a Spirit of Slumber doth uſually precede the greateſt Judgments.</p>
                  <p>And this Suſpicion is the more increas'd in me, when I conſider how eaſily our <hi>Diviſions</hi> might be compos'd, and the <hi>Miſchiefs and Confuſions,</hi> which ſeem coming on like a Torrent, be prevented, were it not for a <hi>Spirit of Faction</hi> and <hi>Self-Intereſt,</hi> but miſtaken Intereſt in all Parties, and the <hi>Abuſes</hi> put upon all by the falſe Pretences of a few <hi>Sons of Bichri,</hi> who do more harm at home, than all our foreign Adverſaries abroad, and were it not for thoſe, 'twere eaſy to break all their meaſures more effectually, than all our Forces both by Sea and Land are like to do.</p>
                  <p>But one of the greateſt <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappineſſes of Mankind</hi> in the State they are fall'n unto, is that they are generally like a <hi>Flock of ſilly</hi> Sheep, which are either quietly fed and preſerv'd in Safety, by faithful and careful Shepherds, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd
<pb facs="tcp:38977:10"/>or frighted into Danger and Miſchief by ſuch as are careleſs of them, but get in among them to ſerve themſelves of them for ſome Deſigns of their own. For they are very few who act upon ſound and ſolid Judgment, but moſt upon common Opinion, receiv'd by Education, taken up upon inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Apprehenſion, or impos'd upon them by the Craſt and Subtlety of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning Men, who abuſe their Hopes and Confidence only to ſerve themſelves.</p>
                  <p>Out of Pity therefore for the <hi>innocent Flocks,</hi> that they may beware of ſuch Shepherds, and of the Spirit of Faction in all Parties, are theſe Papers now publiſh'd. My <hi>Kindneſs</hi> expreſt <hi>to the honeſt Quakers</hi> may poſſibly be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtru'd by ſome, eſpecially of their ſharpeſt Adverſaries: But, beſides other reaſons, the <hi>monſtrous prevalence of the Spirit of Faction,</hi> even in ſuch as are in a ſuffering Caſe, and Perſons otherwiſe of Learning and Ability to conſider, and yet will not receive the Truths they cannot fairly reſiſt, was a ſpecial Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to me to accept the Invitations for farther Conference from a People ſo deſpis'd in the ſight of the Learned; tho I never uſe to decline to <hi>anſwer</hi> any, either <hi>by Word or Writing,</hi> whom I find ſerious and pertinent. And I do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare I do it ſincerely and heartily, and will not be aſham'd to aſſert and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain whatever <hi>Truth</hi> there is amongſt them or any others, againſt any or all Oppoſers of it. For <hi>Truth and Righteouſneſs,</hi> by the Grace of God, I will not deſert in what Party ſoever. And if the honeſt and well-meaning People of this Party will accept of my Advice and Aſſiſtance, I do not deſpair, thro Divine Aſſiſtance, but to help them, who are now the moſt deſpis'd of all Sects, to become as truly honourable in real Worth and Virtue as any of them all; and to maintain their Cauſe, not only by Principles of Religion, but alſo by the true Principles of the Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But for thoſe Troublers of our Peace and Unity, thoſe <hi>Roman Catholick Miſſioners</hi> and <hi>Quaker Miniſters,</hi> who obſtinately reſiſt the Truth, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with any ſound reaſon gainſay, and notwithſtanding continue with their Sophiſtry and ſpecious Pretences to <hi>deceive the People,</hi> if the State pleaſe but to afford me a reaſonable Favour and Aſſiſtance of the Civil Authority, I hope I ſhall eaſily demonſtrate that they are ſo juſtly puniſhable by the I aws of this Nation, antecedent to thoſe made againſt them in particular, as will leave them utterly inexcuſable, and promote a good Service both to God and Man, much more effectually. Which might have been put in practice before this time, if ſuch as, not long ſince, made the laſt great Clamour againſt the <hi>Growth of Popery,</hi> had really deſigned to ſtop it, and not merely to abuſe the People, to ingratiate themſelves with them, that they might uſe them at pleaſure for their own Advantage. This was undoubtedly <hi>the Myſtery of the unreaſonable be verity of that Act,</hi> which has hitherto ſerv'd rather for a <hi>Cover</hi> than any <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint</hi> of that Growth; and poſſibly might be ſo intended by ſuch <hi>Juglers with all Parties</hi> for their own Intereſt; who, when once diſcover'd, can never after be ſafely truſted by any, or will eaſily by ſuch as are wiſe.</p>
                  <p>I know not any greater Service, which can be done to this Nation at this time, than to <hi>undeceive</hi> and <hi>diſabuſe</hi> the innocent Flocks of this diſtracted and divided People, by detecting the <hi>Deceivers</hi> and their ſeveral <hi>Arts and Abuſes;</hi> nor any one, who has endeavour'd it upon ſo clear and certain Principles in all reſpects, or with equal Candour, Impartiality and Conviction, as I have done. And therefore, by how much the greater are the Evidences of my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity,
<pb n="y" facs="tcp:38977:11"/>Fidelity, and conſtant Zeal for your Service; that is, for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of my Country, ſo much the more notorious is the Iniquity and evil Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, of ſuch as by malicious Defamations, have not only groſly abus'd me (which I could eaſily have born had that been all) but diſabled me from farther Proſecution of that Service hitherto, to which I am ſo heartily and intirely affected; and the greater is the Evidence againſt them, that they are no true Friends to our Country, but <hi>unfaithful treacherous Deceivers,</hi> who, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſpecious Pretences, ſeek to ſerve themſelves, without due regard, if any at all, to the Service of their Country. And they are of <hi>two ſorts,</hi> either ſuch as are or have been our <hi>Truſtees in Parliament,</hi> or of the <hi>Clergy of the Church of England.</hi> And theſe latter have not only <hi>injur'd</hi> me and <hi>hinder'd</hi> me in your Service, but brought a foul <hi>Scandal</hi> upon the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Conſideration of that may be left to the ſupreme Authority, ſo lately aſſerted in all Cauſes as well Spiritual as Temporal.</p>
                  <p>But for the others, who have not only <hi>injur'd</hi> me, and done you that <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervice,</hi> but moreover foully broken the <hi>Truſt repos'd in them,</hi> in betraying one of our principal and moſt neceſſary Rights; which if once loſt our <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> become our <hi>Maſters,</hi> and more likely by their <hi>Tricking</hi> to bring all into Confuſion, than ever to do any thing truly for the Honor or Safety of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I muſt therefore recommend that unto you with this FAITHFUL ADMONITION AND ADVICE: Neglect no longer your own Intereſt at your COUNTY COURTS: Give there your <hi>Inſtructions</hi> well conſider'd to your Truſtees, when you chooſe them, and there <hi>confer</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly concerning their Behaviour, and as occaſion requires, from thence <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh</hi> them of what you ſee neceſſary: And at your next Court, or as ſoon as may be, aſſert, like true <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> that <hi>antient, fundamental neceſſary Right</hi> of every Commoner of <hi>England,</hi> to have his <hi>Petitions</hi> for proper mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to be preſented to the Houſe of Commons, by his Repreſentatives, and to be read, heard and conſider'd, and duly anſwer'd there; and the <hi>Duty of your Truſtees</hi> to inquire into the Miſcarriages in that reſpect. This may be done alſo at your <hi>General Quarter Seſſions,</hi> and by <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>Buroughs</hi> at their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Courts,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <date>
                        <hi>June</hi> 19. 1704.</date>
                     <signed>Your Faithful Friend, Fellow-Commoner, and ready Servant in all things of Truth and Righteouſneſs, <hi>Edward Stephens.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38977:11"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
